<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Fôrça Bruta! - misc</title><link href="https://reis-r.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://reis-r.github.io/feeds/misc.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://reis-r.github.io/</id><updated>2020-12-23T18:48:13-03:00</updated><entry><title>저는 한국어를 조금 할 수 있어요!</title><link href="https://reis-r.github.io/jeoneun-hangugeoreul-jogeum-hal-su-isseoyo.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-12-23T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2020-12-23T18:48:13-03:00</updated><author><name>Rony Reis</name></author><id>tag:reis-r.github.io,2020-12-23:/jeoneun-hangugeoreul-jogeum-hal-su-isseoyo.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today I received the certificate for my first semester of Korean Language classes by the Korean Education Institute of São Paulo.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Learning the basics of Esperanto when I was 15 opened my eyes to language learning. I grew up when video games were not translated to Portuguese (my native language), and having English everywhere around me, I managed to start catching meaning. I actually played with dictionaries as a boy, reading random pages and having joy when finding a weird word to play with. Learning a language is very rewarding, it allows you to get in touch with different cultures, textbooks to study another subjects, and just following the news… However, there is more to that: you learn new ways of thinking. I believe there is something in language learning that boosts the very core of our cognition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I received the certificate for my first semester of Korean Language classes by the Korean Education Institute of São Paulo (KEISP). I am very grateful for this; it is a beautiful language, with an amazing writing system. The Korean people is blessed with good cuisine, entertainment and stunning landscapes. It is always nice to have a goal, so my aim (for now – of course) is to be able to follow the &lt;em&gt;League Champions Korea&lt;/em&gt; (LCK) games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The language is not as any other I have ever seen. Nevertheless, it is also the first language I learn with the help of a teacher from ground up. There are many challenges (I’m looking at you, ㄷ, ㄸ, and ㅌ), and I am far form proficient, but that is the start of an exciting journey. I started it with the right foot.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="personal"></category><category term="languages"></category></entry><entry><title>Udacity's Microsoft Scholarship Program</title><link href="https://reis-r.github.io/udacitys-microsoft-scholarship-program.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-10-16T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2020-10-16T14:21:08-03:00</updated><author><name>Rony Reis</name></author><id>tag:reis-r.github.io,2020-10-16:/udacitys-microsoft-scholarship-program.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I'm one of the 300 selected for the Machine Learning Scholarship Program!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;On October 13, I received the very good news I was selected for the Scholarship program at Udacity, for learning Machine Learning on the Azure Platform. I'm very happy for this. I already started my journey through the material and noticed they made good changes to the lab environment, which I had some problems with on phase 1 of the selection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surely this will boost my skills, a lot!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src="https://mclick.udacity.com/z/omxox0h05?uid=52526295-1901-47c2-8604-f24fb55d1bc4&amp;mid=fd3e85c2-4473-4368-bf75-e7518e11634d&amp;bsft_ek=2020-10-13T17%3A51%3A18Z&amp;bsft_mime_type=html&amp;bsft_link_id=17" alt="Scholarship Badge" style="width:40%;max-width:400px;"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="irl"></category><category term="misc"></category><category term="studies"></category></entry><entry><title>Three months without Emacs: do I miss it?</title><link href="https://reis-r.github.io/three-months-without-emacs-do-i-miss-it.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-10-04T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2020-10-04T11:22:36-03:00</updated><author><name>Rony Reis</name></author><id>tag:reis-r.github.io,2020-10-04:/three-months-without-emacs-do-i-miss-it.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Three months passed since I used Emacs for anything, here is what I miss (or don't)!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I used to do it all in Emacs, checking my email, chatting, reading news, planning tasks and even listening to internet radio and podcasts. I used spit a thousand commands per second with the amazing &lt;a href="https://github.com/xahlee/xah-fly-keys"&gt;xah-fly-keys&lt;/a&gt; modal editing. I was very productive indeed, I didn't even launch X if I didn't needed to. In fact, I had a Nix script that built Emacs and it's packages together with my system stuff, it was basically Nix/Emacs! hehehe&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, I narrowed my studies to Python and Data Science, and a graphical interface turned into something just so essential, then came Jupyter, and I bought a new computer which came with Windows... I felt I could try something really different to make my life more sane (because I try to do so many different things in life), and rather than just changing my Window Manager, I re-evaluated my whole toolset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For most production stuff I used Emacs for, like to-do lists and calendar, I'm using Outlook now, synchronizing with my phone is always good. In fact, most non-programming things I did before now are done faster and more nicely (UX-wise) with office tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For Notebooks (my work tool as a data guy), &lt;a href="https://github.com/millejoh/emacs-ipython-notebook"&gt;EIN&lt;/a&gt; is good. But I got really used to Jupyter Lab, it's way easier to configure. I also like to use the Google Colab platform when I need to show someone the code (it makes a lot easier to share). In the R side, RStudio is just too good to ignore, it's like "Excel for serious math". Ok, this is like 4 different interfaces to learn, but once you get good at them, I think production goes up so much, and most of them are way easier to learn than Emacs. Maybe I'm just experiencing the universal facts of &lt;a href="https://captainalan.github.io/pelican-test/qwerty-theory.html"&gt;QWERTY Theory&lt;/a&gt;. I feel a lot more productive just not trying &lt;em&gt;too hard&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only thing I really miss Emacs is actually coding (this sounds silly!). I have been using the Atom editor, which looks like a good Emacs replacement, but I really could not dig too much into it. (&lt;em&gt;Help! I don't see a RELP!&lt;/em&gt;) I miss coding modes for more hipster languages like the &lt;a href="https://docs.hylang.org/en/stable/"&gt;Hy Programming Language&lt;/a&gt;, which I love. I'll probably install Emacs soon to play with this language again, I just need to decide: MSYS, Cygwin, WSL... Maybe native?&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="emacs"></category><category term="unix"></category><category term="productivity"></category></entry><entry><title>New computer, strange freezes and silly solution</title><link href="https://reis-r.github.io/new-computer-strange-freezes-and-silly-solution.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-07-29T00:00:00-03:00</published><updated>2020-08-08T11:48:19-03:00</updated><author><name>Rony Reis</name></author><id>tag:reis-r.github.io,2020-07-29:/new-computer-strange-freezes-and-silly-solution.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I bought a new computer and it came with a weird bug that took me months to fix.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;After enduring for 7 years, my Lenovo Ideapad S400 started to give up on me. It was my main and mostly only machine. I wished to buy a Thinkpad as an upgrade since I liked it so much, but with the whole COVID-19 crisis, the prices skyrocketed. I ended up buying an Acer Aspire 3 with AMD processor/video card, it was a more cost-effective choice than another Ideapad. I'm quite happy with it so far, and I'm enjoying being able to play some modern games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But as soon as I got everything setup on the new machine, it started to freeze randomly. It would happen on random times, usually when I used a lot of RAM. It happened a lot of times when I was using Jupyter Kernels, and mostly when changing context from one application to another. The mouse wouldn't move, sound would glitch, all the system froze. I came to the point of reinstalling Windows 10 altogether two times, trying different driver versions and software to troubleshot the problem. I was praying for it not to be a factory defect since I could not afford not having a computer for work and study. The solution was quite surprising for me...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Two months of intensive testing and freezing and rebooting passed. I tried changing habits and not opening lots of programs and keeping them opened as I did previously. But what would be the point of having a newer, faster machine, then?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then I searched for something I was sure it was NOT the problem, since I had used for my entire life and it has never failed me: Veracrypt. It turns out Veracrypt &lt;strong&gt;was&lt;/strong&gt; just the cause of the problem. I had always used it's full disk encryption on Windows, but I used Windows 8 previously, and looks like with newer versions of Windows 10 it has a bug where the encryption keys end up in the paging file and deadlocking the system. You can find about it &lt;a href="https://sourceforge.net/p/veracrypt/discussion/general/thread/f6e7f623d0/"&gt;clicking on this thread&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the solution was disabling full system encryption, encrypting only sensitive files (and using Window's native system encryption). Of course, I could always go back to Linux, or dual booting, but I'm enjoying what became of Windows 10. I'll sure write about my experience on another posts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="misc"></category><category term="personal"></category><category term="computers"></category></entry><entry><title>Happy 2020!</title><link href="https://reis-r.github.io/happy-2020.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2020-02-18T19:46:35-03:00</published><updated>2020-04-19T00:52:08-03:00</updated><author><name>Rony Reis</name></author><id>tag:reis-r.github.io,2020-02-18:/happy-2020.html</id><summary type="html">
      &lt;p&gt;I just wanted to say Happy New Year to the internet before it's just too late to do so!🤡&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Actually, I've been pretty busy, with new job and moving to another town. But I'm fine and the sun is shinning brighter for me every day. I've been doing all sort …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
      &lt;p&gt;I just wanted to say Happy New Year to the internet before it's just too late to do so!🤡&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Actually, I've been pretty busy, with new job and moving to another town. But I'm fine and the sun is shinning brighter for me every day. I've been doing all sort of things but I don't have a project worth talking about. I completed some &lt;a href="https://cognitiveclass.ai/"&gt;IBM Cognitive Class&lt;/a&gt; courses (you can see my badges &lt;a href="https://www.youracclaim.com/badges/10cf39d5-8a2f-45db-8f76-5b288e233a04/linked_in_profile"&gt;clicking here&lt;/a&gt;!).&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I'm now focusing on the MOC "&lt;a href="https://www.udacity.com/course/data-wrangling-with-mongodb--ud032"&gt;Data Wrangling with MongoDB&lt;/a&gt;" as "main goal". I still playing with lisp on my "free" off-line time, doing some basic CL exercises from Norvig's book &lt;a href="https://github.com/norvig/paip-lisp"&gt;Paradigms of Artificial Intelligence Programming&lt;/a&gt;, but I just bought Mark Watson's &lt;a href="https://leanpub.com/hy-lisp-python"&gt;new book on the Hy language&lt;/a&gt; and will go with it for now on, it looks really amazing.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;So this is it, the year really started, as some say, "LIT"!&lt;/p&gt;
    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="meta"></category><category term="personal"></category></entry><entry><title>League in numbers (2019)</title><link href="https://reis-r.github.io/league-in-numbers-2019.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-11-26T12:06:00-03:00</published><updated>2020-04-19T23:40:14-03:00</updated><author><name>Rony Reis</name></author><id>tag:reis-r.github.io,2019-11-26:/league-in-numbers-2019.html</id><content type="html">
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.twitch.tv/boicolorido"&gt;I started streaming me doing my homework project&lt;/a&gt;, and this is the result: &lt;a href="https://app.powerbi.com/view?r=eyJrIjoiNjRiYjJjZWEtOGE1OC00MzM2LWFhNWUtYjU1NWQyYWVmY2NkIiwidCI6IjEyYjlhNTNlLTcwYWQtNDQzOC1hY2UzLWE4YjE2ZGM5OGZmYyIsImMiOjh9"&gt;it's a dashboard of the pro League of Legends games in 2019&lt;/a&gt;.
        &lt;br&gt;
      &lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This is still a work in progress&lt;/strong&gt;. I may update it.&lt;/p&gt;
    </content><category term="misc"></category></entry><entry><title>My Twitch channel</title><link href="https://reis-r.github.io/my-twitch-channel.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-11-19T22:28:00-03:00</published><updated>2020-04-19T00:52:48-03:00</updated><author><name>Rony Reis</name></author><id>tag:reis-r.github.io,2019-11-19:/my-twitch-channel.html</id><summary type="html">
      &lt;p&gt;Hello, I have been busy. I created a Twitch channel so I could stream my games (mostly League of Legends, PUBG...). It's on portuguese but if you interact in english I may reply with no problem. If I get confident about it I may even do a talk show about …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
      &lt;p&gt;Hello, I have been busy. I created a Twitch channel so I could stream my games (mostly League of Legends, PUBG...). It's on portuguese but if you interact in english I may reply with no problem. If I get confident about it I may even do a talk show about computer and data science stuff instead of gaming. Anyway, the link to the stream is https://www.twitch.tv/boicolorido&lt;/p&gt;
    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="meta"></category><category term="personal"></category><category term="twitch"></category><category term="streaming"></category><category term="content"></category><category term="gaming"></category><category term="league"></category></entry><entry><title>Configuring the DVORAK International with dead keys AND DVORAK keyboards on X11</title><link href="https://reis-r.github.io/configuring-the-dvorak-international-with-dead-keys-and-dvorak-keyboards-on-x11.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-07-27T22:28:00-03:00</published><updated>2020-04-19T00:55:12-03:00</updated><author><name>Rony Reis</name></author><id>tag:reis-r.github.io,2019-07-27:/configuring-the-dvorak-international-with-dead-keys-and-dvorak-keyboards-on-x11.html</id><summary type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;
      I have been using the &lt;a href="https://www.dvorak-keyboard.com"&gt;DVORAK&lt;/a&gt; keyboard layout for years, and I'm really glad I did it, because it forced me to learn how to properly type. The problem comes when you want to input diacritics used in some languages (things like "ú" and "õ"). My usual setup was: using …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
    &lt;p&gt;
      I have been using the &lt;a href="https://www.dvorak-keyboard.com"&gt;DVORAK&lt;/a&gt; keyboard layout for years, and I'm really glad I did it, because it forced me to learn how to properly type. The problem comes when you want to input diacritics used in some languages (things like "ú" and "õ"). My usual setup was: using setxkbmap to turn on the DVORAK keyboard and using something like &lt;a href=""&gt;SCIM&lt;/a&gt;/&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Intelligent_Input_Bus"&gt;iBus&lt;/a&gt; to activate the "latin-pre" input method to suit my special characters needs. This seems like overkill and I was searching for an alternative.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;It turns out that &lt;a href="https://xfce.org"&gt;XFCE&lt;/a&gt; does change between keyboard layouts and has DVORAK and a DVORAK international keyboard with dead keys, and with no special input method needed at all. I was curious about how this happens (probably some X11 "system-agnostic" configuration) and wanted to make whatever this is to work on &lt;a href="https://xmonad.org/download.html"&gt;xmonad&lt;/a&gt;. After a quick search at my ".config" folder I found a "keyboard-layout.xml" file with all the keyboard configuration.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;p&gt; This is definitely what I was looking for. If you man setxkbmap, you see that there is a correspondence between the properties on the XML and the options for setxkbmap. So my setxkbmap command now looks like: &lt;code&gt;setxkbmap -layout dvorak,us -variant ,dvorak-intl -option grp:alt_space_toggle&lt;/code&gt; and I can simply switch between DVORAK and DVORAK international using &lt;kbd&gt;Alt + Space&lt;/kbd&gt;!
    &lt;/p&gt;
  </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="tips"></category><category term="x11"></category><category term="dvorak"></category><category term="ergonomy"></category><category term="configuration"></category><category term="xorg"></category></entry><entry><title>Hello, World!</title><link href="https://reis-r.github.io/hello-world.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2019-06-27T22:28:00-03:00</published><updated>2020-04-19T00:57:36-03:00</updated><author><name>Rony Reis</name></author><id>tag:reis-r.github.io,2019-06-27:/hello-world.html</id><summary type="html">
      &lt;p&gt;After a lot of thinking, I decided to start writing a blog. I wanted a place to experiment and show what I'm up to lately, and maybe the information I put here will help other people to solve their own problems.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I'm currently getting a graduate degree in Business Intelligence …&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">
      &lt;p&gt;After a lot of thinking, I decided to start writing a blog. I wanted a place to experiment and show what I'm up to lately, and maybe the information I put here will help other people to solve their own problems.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;I'm currently getting a graduate degree in Business Intelligence and Data Science so I will probably have something to share from time to time. Also, my native language isn't English, so this could be a really good way to practice. I do some weird stuff with &lt;a href="https://www.gnu.org/software/emacs/"&gt;GNU Emacs&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href="https://www.dragonflybsd.org/"&gt;DragonFly BSD&lt;/a&gt;, and also some JavaScript programming so you might expect some content about that too.&lt;/p&gt;
    </content><category term="misc"></category><category term="meta"></category><category term="introduction"></category><category term="personal"></category></entry></feed>